Giles Dring

Telephone: +44 (0)7971 548826

Email: giles@dringtech.com LinkedIn: gilesdring
13 Melbourne Street, Hebden Bridge, West Yorkshire HX7 6AS

Profile

I am a Solution Architect, Software Engineer and Technical Consultant with over 20 years' experience delivering data and service projects. I am a strong communicator with an ability to express complex technical concerns to non-technical audiences. My grounding in structured methods fused with repeated experience in agile delivery means I am able to create appropriate design to underpin fast moving team delivery. I have a strong base of technology skills, which enables me to address and learn new platforms and frameworks rapidly.

Expertise

- 5+ years' experience in open data projects as an associate / Head of Delivery for ODI
 Leeds. I have expertise in open data releases and in shaping and delivering prototyping work to explore, refine, improve and showcase the use of open data.
- Excellent analytical and communication skills, capable of presenting detailed technical issues, designs and concepts to clients and peers.
- Extremely fast learner able to acquire and apply technical skills rapidly, as evidenced by role
 as novice Ruby developer, delivering changes to production website within 24 hours of
 contract commencement
- Applied expertise in AWS Cloud technologies including S3, CloudFormation, Lambda Functions, IAM, Elastic Beanstalk, Route 53 and VPC.
- Strong JavaScript / Node.js development skills, including applied knowledge of backend frameworks such as Express and frontend frameworks such as Vue. Expertise in the mocha and jest testing tool stacks. Experience in a wide variety of other programming languages (Ruby, Python, Perl, Java).
- Applied expertise with CI/CD tools supporting DevOps including infrastructure configuration management and automation (Puppet, Ansible, CloudFormation) code and configuration management (Git / GitHub), dependency management (NPM, Ruby Gems and Bundler) and build tools (gulp, rake, rollup, etc).
- Practical knowledge of a wide range of DevOps-related technologies including Docker and the HashiCorp toolchain (Packer, Vagrant), Database platforms (MongoDB, Oracle).

History

Freelance IT Consultant, Dring Technology Solutions Ltd., Feb 2015 to date

Head of Delivery, ODI Leeds

October 2019 to date

I lead the delivery team for ODI Leeds. I am responsible for shaping and delivering Open Data related innovation projects / prototypes. Example projects include:

- External consultant / reviewer for Transport for the North programme which is creating
 Open APIs for disruption and fare data. My role is to review and challenge the published data formats and propose ways that the data can be made useful to a broader user base.
- Designed and delivered data collection and transformation platform for New Statesman /
 Britain Elects General Election result tracking. Design took into account the time sensitivity
 and cognitive load on the journalists entering data

Digital EIA, Connected Places Catapult / ODI Leeds

October 2019 to date

Consultant / data specialist for programme looking into Digitising the Environmental Impact Assessment for construction project planning. Reviewed and commented on the state of technology for Open Data platforms, portals and tooling, and contributed to concept design / roadmap for the future state.

Technical Director, Equal Care Coop start-up

September 2019 to date

I defined the technical architecture for Equal Care Coop's platform which aims to be a trusted and democratic platform for facilitating care work.

- Worked with the founders to refine and prioritise their user journeys and associated requirements
- Synthesized a high-level solution architecture which melded the relationship and transactional aspects
- Created a proof-of-technology using graph and ledger / blockchain database to test the hypotheses contained in the architecture
- Contributed to the hiring of the delivery team

Housing Monitoring Prototype, Connected Places Catapult / ODI Leeds March 2019 to June 2019

Designed and delivered Prototype data matching service for housing completion monitoring. Inferring the state of new housing stock using a variety of open data sources. Assessed existing sources of data and built a platform to ingest, match and report the state of schemes – both in terms of development stage (planning to completion) and number of residences being delivered.

Software Engineer/Application Architect, Digital Delivery Programme, Department for Work and Pensions

October 2017 to February 2020

I worked with a client-led team delivering a major new digital platform in the department. I fulfilled several roles including

 Senior Node.js Software Engineer responsible for mentoring junior staff in Node best practices. I defined the template for creating UI apps using common Node packages.

- Architect responsible for designing a series of microservices and framework components.
 These included a Report Production architecture pattern capable of producing PDF and other format reports and a reusable caching proxy microservice capable of converting a synchronous API into a cached asynchronous service.
- Agile team member able to effectively present complex technical issues to a business audience, and to assist with elaborating user stories to make them deliverable.

• Solution Architect, Infrastructure Modernisation, Bannerboy Creative Agency November 2017 to date

I undertook a series of consultancy and delivery projects for Bannerboy. These aimed to deliver a more flexible and supportable could-native IT infrastructure.

- Re-hosting the multiple Bannerboy websites from in-office servers to AWS Elastic Beanstalk, including defining development pipeline to automate deployment of code updates.
- Provision of custom Git LFS service for storage of large media assets using AWS S3 and Lambda functions.

DevOps Engineer, Private Cloud Infrastructure, Department for Work and Pensions

August 2015 to October 2017

I designed, delivered and supported a range of infrastructure automation projects as the DevOps automation lead in the cloud delivery team.

- Defined the infrastructure configuration management approach for a new private and secure cloud infrastructure. This used Puppet Enterprise to manage all elements of server configuration
- Developed a server build tool using which combined the Puppet configurations with customised server image builds created using Packer. This reduced server build times from 45 minutes manual effort per server to around 5 minutes setup capable of triggering multiple parallel builds.
- Provided technical mentoring and leadership to a client development team creating automation products using a combination of Puppet and Python code.

Consultant, Open Data Institute Leeds

June 2015 to October 2019

Part of the ODI Leeds team, delivering consultancy and workshop engagements to a variety of clients. As of October 2019, I became Head of Delivery at ODI Leeds. Example projects:

- Delivered Open Data Publication approach paper to West Yorkshire Combined Authority advising them on the publication of a transport-related dataset.
- Led rapid prototyping of a digital application form for the Food Standards Agency. This
 demonstrated the concept of translating a paper form to a cloud-native application employing
 single-page web apps hosted in S3. I also delivered an overview of the full design which aimed
 to process the data with Lambda functions connected by Kinesis Data Streams.

• Frontend Designer and Developer, Open Data Institute |une 2015 to August 2015

Working as a consultant contractor to the ODI Labs team, designed, developed and delivered a series of enhancements to the public website and CMS. Developed Ruby code and delivered this to the DevOps environment for automated testing and deployment.

• Business and Technical consultant, local Small / Medium Businesses February 2015 to date

Provided business and IT advice to a number of local business owners, mainly focused on selection and maximizing investment in IT. Sample client profiles include

- Delivered project to relaunch local cinema website, taking into account user needs, cost constraints and in-house skills. Developed plugins to Textpattern CMS (including data design) to support new features.
- Ongoing support for local council IT, including security and backup strategy, desktop PC migration and other general support requirements.
- Supported local Architecture practice in several small projects, including email and website migrations.

IT Architect, IBM United Kingdom, 1998 to February 2015

Enterprise Architect, Department for Work and Pensions (DWP) AD/AM Outsource

Feb 2013 to Feb 2015 (24 months)

Reporting directly for the IBM account CTO, I provided technical oversight of a programme of work worth £15M-£20M per annum. I collaborated with DWP CTO IT Architects to define roadmap for critical programmes of work. I also oversaw governance of change projects, identifying technical and project risks.

• Chief Architect and Design Authority, IBM UK AMS Business Oct 2008 to Feb 2015 (6 years 4 months)

Reporting to the leader of IBM UK Application Management Services, I was responsible for technical oversight of deals ranging from individual changes to complex multi-year multi-million-dollar deals.

Additional Information

Qualifications

- IBM Certified IT Architect 2007 (recertified 2010 and 2013)
- MEng Electronics and Computer Systems Engineering, University of Leeds, 1995

Publications and Patents

- WebSphere Business Integration Server Foundation V5.1 Handbook, IBM Redbook SG24-6318-00
- Integration of software into an existing information technology (IT) infrastructure, US Patent 7949997

Other relevant information

- Governor at Riverside Junior School, Hebden Bridge (2019-date).
- Developed, launched and operated the Hebden Rising hyperlocal website in reaction to the floods which affected Hebden Bridge in December 2015. The site collated and presented information about the local businesses affected by the flooding. Data was stored in Google Fusion tables, and visualised using the Leaflet mapping library.
- Former / founding chair of Hebden Bridge Business Forum (2014-2016)